Asadullah Hill Galib

As a Ph.D. candidate in Computer Science specializing in Machine Learning, I offer a strong background in Software Engineering coupled with a proven track record of multi-disciplinary research collaboration. I am committed to advancing knowledge through innovations in AI. (Link: Explore the avenues of Machine Learning and AI I have worked on)

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science

August 2020 - July 2024 (Expected)

Michigan State University, MI, USA

Advisor: Pang-Ning Tan, Domain: Predictive and Generative Modeling, Time Series, Spatiotemporal, Representation Learning

M.Sc. in Software Engineering

January 2019 - December 2020

University of Dhaka, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Thesis: Significant Features Analysis For Android Malware Detection Using Machine Learning Techniques

B.Sc. in **Software Engineering**

November 2014 - December 2018

University of Dhaka, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Technical Skills (* Proficient)

Programming Languages: Python*, Java, C, C++, PHP, JavaScript, Assembly

AI & Machine Learning: PyTorch*, Lightning*, SK-learn*, Pandas*, NumPy*, Matplotlib*, Anaconda*, MATLAB, Keras **Miscellaneous:** Android*, GCP*, MySQL, Oracle, SQLite, jQuery, React Native, Laravel, Selenium, Git*, Agile, MVC, SRS*

Experience

Researcher (Internship), Frontier Development Lab (FDL) 2022 by NASA and the SETI Institute

June 2022 - August 2022

- Collaborated with a multi-disciplinary team on the NASA challenge: Seismic Insight from Geomagnetic and Ionospheric Data.
- Carried out a statistical analysis that shows promising links between major earthquakes and ionospheric perturbations.
- Created the first machine learning-ready dataset and statistical tool comprising spatiotemporally varying seismic precursors.
- Built machine learning models for forecasting and detecting earthquakes from heterogeneous multivariate time series data.
- Designed a probabilistic model to learn the spatial variability of ionospheric observations around seismic locations.
- Research outcomes: 3 AGU abstracts, 2 papers, 1 technical memo, and 1 NASA NTR.

Graduate Research Assistant, *Michigan State University (CSE)*

January 2022 - Present

• Developing novel deep learning algorithms addressing extreme events within spatio-temporal and time series data.

Graduate Teaching Assistant, *Michigan State University (CSE)*

August 2020 - December 2021

• Lead classes and labs of 260+ students in CSE 102: Algorithmic Thinking and Programming (Python)

Software Developer & Executive Assistant (Internship), Brain Station 23

January 2018 - June 2018

- Developed from scratch and maintained a web application and a mobile application, using Laravel Framework, PHP, MySQL, React-Native, Redux-Saga, Android Studio, Postman and proper version-controlling (Git, SourceTree).
- Analyzed requirement specification and design of an existing system for re-engineering. Analyzed two e-commerce frameworks.

Selected Publications (Full list with details)

- Galib, A. H., Tan, P. N. & Luo, L. (2023, Dec.). SimEXT: Self-supervised Representation Learning for Extreme Values in Time Series. In ICDM 2023 (20% acceptance rate).
- Galib, A. H., McDonald, A., Tan, P. N. & Luo, L. (2023, Aug.). Self-Recover: Forecasting Block Maxima in Time Series from Predictors with Disparate Temporal Coverage using Self-Supervised Learning. In IJCAI 2023 (15% acceptance rate).
- Galib, A. H., McDonald, A., Wilson, T., Luo, L., & Tan, P. N. (2022, Jul.). DeepExtrema: A Deep Learning Approach for Forecasting Block Maxima in Time Series Data. In IJCAI 2022 (15% acceptance rate).
- Wilson, T., McDonald, A., Galib, A. H., Luo, L., & Tan, P. N. (2022, Aug.). Beyond Point Prediction: Capturing Zero-Inflated & Heavy-Tailed Spatiotemporal Data with Deep Extreme Mixture Models. In KDD 2022 (15% acceptance rate).
- Cullen*, L., Galib*, A. H., Smith*, A. W., Varshney*, D., Brown, E., Chi, P., ... & Svoboda, F. (2022, Dec.). Can We Forecast And Detect Earthquakes From Heterogeneous Multivariate Time Series Data? In ICBINB@ NeurIPS 2022.

Academic and Research Projects (Full list with Details)

- Predicting GitHub Issues Lifetime using Machine Learning and Topic Modeling (LDA): It outperforms the previous approach with a high precision and f1- measure. Also, it extracts distinguishable and comprehensible topics from issues. PDF.
- Analyzing co-authorship network: Centrality Measure, Link Prediction, and Community Detection: It analyzes a network of co-authorship relations, predicts missing links and detects community using the network modularity algorithm.